When I wrote my memoir,
عندما كتبت مذكراتي،
the publishers were really confused.
كان الناشر جد حائر،
Was it about me as a child refugee,
هل هي عني كطفلة لاجئة
or as a woman who set up a high-tech software company back in the 1960s,
أم كسيدة أنشأت شركة برمجيات في الستينات،
one that went public
شركة دخلت البورصة
and eventually employed over 8,500 people?
وتشغل أكثر من 8.500 شخص؟
Or was it as a mother of an autistic child?
أو كأم لطفل مصاب بالتوحد؟
Or as a philanthropist that's now given away serious money?
أو كمُحِبة للخير تقدم مساعدات مادية مهمة؟
Well, it turns out, I'm all of these.
على ما يبدو أنني كل ذلك.
So let me tell you my story.
لذا دعوني اخبركم بقصتي.
All that I am stems from when I got onto a train in Vienna,
كل ما أنا عليه الآن هو وليد لحظة ركوبي للقطار في فيينا
part of the Kindertransport that saved nearly 10,000 Jewish children
الذي كان جزء من عملية نقل الأطفال التي أنقذت ما يقارب 10.000 طفل يهودي
from Nazi Europe.
من براثن النازية في أوروبا.
I was five years old, clutching the hand of my nine-year-old sister
كنت في الخامسة من عمري أتعلق بيد أختي الكبرى ذات التسع سنوات
and had very little idea as to what was going on.
وكنت غير مدركة تماما لما يجري من حولي.
"What is England and why am I going there?"
"ما هي انجلترا ولما أنا ذاهبت إلى هناك؟"
I'm only alive because so long ago, I was helped by generous strangers.
وأنا على قيد الحياة فقط لأنه منذ وقت طويل ساعدني بعض الغرباء الكرام.
I was lucky, and doubly lucky to be later reunited
كنت محظوظة، وجد محظوظة لأني عثرت لاحقا
with my birth parents.
على والدي الحقيقيين.
But, sadly, I never bonded with them again.
ولكن مع الأسف علاقتي بهما لم ترجع إلى عهدها قط
But I've done more in the seven decades since that miserable day
لكني حققت الكثير خلال العقود السبعة منذ ذلك اليوم الكئيب
when my mother put me on the train
الذي وضعتني فيه أمي بالقطار
than I would ever have dreamed possible.
أكثر مما كنت أحلم به.
And I love England, my adopted country,
وأنا أحب انجلترا، بلدي الذي احتضنني،
with a passion that perhaps only someone who has lost their human rights can feel.
كما قد يفعل شخص خسر أبسط حقوقه الإنسانية.
I decided to make mine a life that was worth saving.
فقررت حينها أن أجعل من حياتي شيئا يستحق الذكرى.
And then, I just got on with it.
لأستقل بعدها قطار الحياة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Let me take you back to the early 1960s.
دعوني أعد بكم إلى بدايات الستينات.
To get past the gender issues of the time,
لأتخطى القضايا الجنسانية القائمة آنذاك،
I set up my own software house at one of the first such startups in Britain.
أنشأت شركة برمجيات كواحدة من الشركات الناشئة الأولى من نوعها ببريطانيا.
But it was also a company of women, a company for women,
لكنها كانت أيضا شركة نسائية وللنساء
an early social business.
وكانت من أوائل الشركات الاجتماعية.
And people laughed at the very idea because software, at that time,
وقد سخر الناس وقتها من الفكرة، لكون البرمجيات
was given away free with hardware.
كانت توزع بالمجان مع الأجهزة.
Nobody would buy software, certainly not from a woman.
فلا أحد سيرغب بشراء البرمجيات، وبالتأكيد ليس من عند امرأة.
Although women were then coming out of the universities with decent degrees,
فبالرغم من أن النساء وقتها كن يحصلن على شهادات جيدة من الجامعات،
there was a glass ceiling to our progress.
إلا أننا واجهنا بابًا مغلقًا حال دون تقدمنا.
And I'd hit that glass ceiling too often,
وقد طرقت كثيرا ذاك الباب
and I wanted opportunities for women.
وأردت أن تحظى المرأة بالمزيد من الفرص.
I recruited professionally qualified women who'd left the industry on marriage,
لذا استخدمت النساء المؤهلات مهنيا اللواتي تركن العمل بعد الزواج
or when their first child was expected
أو بعد أول حمل
and structured them into a home-working organization.
ونظمتهن في إطار مؤسسة للعمل من المنزل.
We pioneered the concept of women going back into the workforce
لقد أسسنا لمفهوم عودة النساء إلى العمل
after a career break.
بعد انقطاع مهني.
We pioneered all sorts of new, flexible work methods:
كما أسسنا لجميع أنواع طرق العمل الجديدة والمرنة:
job shares, profit-sharing, and eventually, co-ownership
كمشاركة العمل والأرباح وفي النهاية الملكية المشتركة
when I took a quarter of the company into the hands of the staff
عندما نقلت ملكية ربع الشركة للعمال
at no cost to anyone but me.
دون تحميل التكاليف لأحد غيري أنا.
For years, I was the first woman this, or the only woman that.
ولسنوات كنت أوصف بالمرأة الأولى في هذا أو الوحيدة في ذاك.
And in those days, I couldn't work on the stock exchange,
وفي تلك الأيام لم يكن بإمكاني العمل في البورصة
I couldn't drive a bus or fly an airplane.
أو قيادة حافلة أو طائرة.
Indeed, I couldn't open a bank account without my husband's permission.
بل إنني لم أكن أقدر على فتح حساب مصرفي دون موافقة زوجي.
My generation of women fought the battles for the right to work
لقد خاض جيلي من النساء معارك من أجل حق العمل
and the right for equal pay.
والمساواة في الأجور.
Nobody really expected much from people at work or in society
فلا أحد كان ينتظر شيئا من الناس في العمل أو في المجتمع
because all the expectations then
لأن جميع الانتظارات كانت وقتها
were about home and family responsibilities.
مرتبطة بالمنزل والمسؤوليات الأسرية.
And I couldn't really face that,
ولم أكن أستطيع مواجهة ذلك،
so I started to challenge the conventions of the time,
لذا بدأت في مواجهة أعراف ذاك الوقت،
even to the extent of changing my name from "Stephanie" to "Steve"
لدرجة أنني غيرت اسمي من "ستيفاني" إلى "ستيف"
in my business development letters,
في رسائلي للتطوير المهني،
so as to get through the door before anyone realized
لأعبر الباب قبل أن يدرك أحد
that he was a she.
بأن هو كانت هي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
My company, called Freelance Programmers, and that's precisely what it was,
لم تكن شركتي المسماة فريلانس بروغرامرز، وهي إسم على مسمى،
couldn't have started smaller: on the dining room table,
لتبدأ بشكل أصغر: من على طاولة غرفة المعيشة
and financed by the equivalent of 100 dollars in today's terms,
وبرأسمال يعادل 100 دولار اليوم
and financed by my labor and by borrowing against the house.
وذلك بتمويل من عملي وبواسطة قرض بضمان المنزل.
My interests were scientific, the market was commercial --
وكانت اهتماماتي علمية والسوق تجارية --
things such as payroll, which I found rather boring.
اهتمامات كجدول الأجور الذي كنت أعتبره أمرا مملا.
So I had to compromise with operational research work,
لذا كان علي التسوية بأعمال البحوث التشغيلية
which had the intellectual challenge that interested me
التي كانت تحتوي على التحدي الفكري الذي يهمني
and the commercial value that was valued by the clients:
والقيمة التجارية المهمة للزبائن:
things like scheduling freight trains,
أشياء كجدولة قطارات الشحن
time-tabling buses, stock control, lots and lots of stock control.
والجداول الزمنية للحافلات ومراقبة المخزون، الكثير والكثير من مراقبة المخزون
And eventually, the work came in.
وفي النهاية، بدأ العمل يعطي أكله.
We disguised the domestic and part-time nature of the staff
بحيث غطينا طبيعة العمل من المنزل والدوام الجزئي لفريقنا
by offering fixed prices, one of the very first to do so.
من خلال تطبيقنا لسياسة الأسعار الثابتة، وكنا أول شركة تقوم بذلك.
And who would have guessed that the programming
ومن كان ليحزر بأن برمجة
of the black box flight recorder of Supersonic Concord
الصندوق الأسود لطائرة الكونكورد
would have been done by a bunch of women working in their own homes.
أنجز من طرف مجموعة نساء يعملن من منازلهن.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
All we used was a simple "trust the staff" approach
كل ما اعتمدنا عليه هو مقاربة "ثق بفريق عملك"
and a simple telephone.
وهاتف عادي للتواصل.
We even used to ask job applicants, "Do you have access to a telephone?"
بل إننا سألنا المرشحات للعمل، "هل لديك هاتف؟"
An early project was to develop software standards
كان أول مشاريعنا متعلق بتطوير معايير برمجيات
on management control protocols.
بروتوكولات الرقابة الإدارية.
And software was and still is a maddeningly hard-to-control activity,
وكانت البرمجيات ولا تزال نشاطًا يصعب التحكم به
so that was enormously valuable.
لذا كان مشروعنا ذا قيمة كبيرة.
We used the standards ourselves,
لقد استعملنا المعايير بأنفسنا
we were even paid to update them over the years,
حتى أننا تقاضينا أجرا مقابل تحيينها لسنوات
and eventually, they were adopted by NATO.
وفي النهاية استخدمت من طرف حلف الشمال الأطلسي.
Our programmers -- remember, only women,
وقد عمل مبرمجينا -- تذكروا أغلبهم من النساء
including gay and transgender --
ومن بينهن فئات أخرى --
worked with pencil and paper to develop flowcharts
بالقلم والورقة لتطوير مخططات هيكلية
defining each task to be done.
تحدد كل مهمة ينبغي إنجازها.
And they then wrote code, usually machine code,
وقد كتبن اللغة وغالبا ما كانت لغة آلة
sometimes binary code,
وأحيانا شفرة ثنائية
which was then sent by mail to a data center
ترسل بعدها بالبريد لمركز البيانات
to be punched onto paper tape or card
لتنقل على شريط أو بطاقة ورقية مثقبة
and then re-punched, in order to verify it.
ثم تعاد الكرة مرة أخرى للتأكد.
All this, before it ever got near a computer.
كل هذا قبل الاقتراب من الحاسوب حتى.
That was programming in the early 1960s.
وكانت هذه هي البرمجة في بداية الستينات.
In 1975, 13 years from startup,
وفي 1975، أي 13 سنة منذ انطلاق شركتنا،
equal opportunity legislation came in in Britain
صدر قانون المساواة في الفرص ببريطانيا
and that made it illegal to have our pro-female policies.
وبذلك أصبحت سياستنا الداعمة للمرأة غير قانونية.
And as an example of unintended consequences,
وكمثال على النتائج الغير متوقعة
my female company had to let the men in.
كان على شركتي النسائية أن تفتح أبوابها للرجال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When I started my company of women,
عندما أطلقت شركتي النسائية
the men said, "How interesting, because it only works because it's small."
قال عنها الرجال: "هذا مثير، إنها تعمل فقط لأنها صغيرة الحجم."
And later, as it became sizable, they accepted, "Yes, it is sizable now,
وبعد أن أصبحت أكبر، تقبلوا الأمر قائلين: "نعم، لقد كبرت الآن
but of no strategic interest."
لكنها بدون أية أهمية استراتيجية."
And later, when it was a company valued at over three billion dollars,
ولاحقا عندما قدرت قيمتها بأكثر من 3 ملايير دولار
and I'd made 70 of the staff into millionaires,
وجعلت 70 شخصا من فريق العمل يصبحون أثرياء
they sort of said, "Well done, Steve!"
قالوا شيئا مثل: "أحسنت عملا ستيف!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
You can always tell ambitious women by the shape of our heads:
يمكنكم دائما معرفة النساء الطموحات من خلال شكل رؤوسهن:
They're flat on top for being patted patronizingly.
فهي مسطحة من الأعلى بسبب الربت الأبوي الذي تلقته.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
And we have larger feet to stand away from the kitchen sink.
وأقدامنا أكبر لكي نقف بعيدا عن بالوعة المطبخ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Let me share with you two secrets of success:
دعوني أشارككم سرين من أسرار النجاح:
Surround yourself with first-class people and people that you like;
أحيطوا انفسكم بأشخاص ذوي همم عالية وأشخاص تحبونهم؛
and choose your partner very, very carefully.
واختاروا شركاء حياتكم بحرص كبير.
Because the other day when I said, "My husband's an angel,"
لأنه عندما قلت في المرة الماضية: "زوجي ملاك"
a woman complained -- "You're lucky," she said,
اشتكت امرأة وقالت: "أنت محظوظة"
"mine's still alive."
"زوجي ما زال حيا."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If success were easy, we'd all be millionaires.
فلو كان النجاح أمرا سهلا لكنا جميعا أثرياء.
But in my case, it came in the midst of family trauma and indeed, crisis.
لكن في حالتي جاء النجاح وسط صدمة بل أزمة عائلية.
Our late son, Giles, was an only child, a beautiful, contented baby.
رزقنا بعد مدة بابن وحيد هو جايلز، كان جميلا ومرحا.
And then, at two and a half,
وفي سن الثانية والنصف،
like a changeling in a fairy story,
وكطفل مبدول في قصة خيالية،
he lost the little speech that he had
خسر الكلمات القليلة التي كان يعرفها
and turned into a wild, unmanageable toddler.
وأصبح طفلا شرسا وخارجا عن السيطرة.
Not the terrible twos;
لم تكن تلك فترة السنتين؛
he was profoundly autistic and he never spoke again.
بل أصيب بتوحد شديد لم يتكلم بعده قط.
Giles was the first resident in the first house of the first charity that I set up
وكان جايلز أول مقيم في أول بيت بأول جمعية خيرية أنشأتها
to pioneer services for autism.
للعمل في الخدمات المتعلقة بالتوحد.
And then there's been a groundbreaking Prior's Court school
لتظهر بعدها مدرسة بريورس كورت الرائدة
for pupils with autism
في العمل مع التلاميذ المصابين بالتوحد
and a medical research charity, again, all for autism.
وفي العمل الطبي الخيري المتعلق بالتوحد.
Because whenever I found a gap in services, I tried to help.
لأنه كلما وجدت فراغا في الخدمات، حاولت المساعدة.
I like doing new things and making new things happen.
فأنا أحب القيام بأشياء جديدة والمساعدة على تحقيق الأشياء الجديدة.
And I've just started a three-year think tank for autism.
وقد أطلقت مؤخرا مركز دراسات للتوحد منذ 3 سنوات.
And so that some of my wealth does go back to the industry from which it stems,
ولكي يعود جزء من ثروتي إلى الصناعة التي كانت مصدرا لها،
I've also founded the Oxford Internet Institute
أسست أيضا معهد أكسفورد للإنترنت
and other IT ventures.
ومشاريع أخرى لتكنولوجيا المعلومات.
The Oxford Internet Institute focuses not on the technology,
ولا يركز معهد أكسفورد للإنترنت على التقنية وحسب
but on the social, economic, legal and ethical issues of the Internet.
بل أيضا على القضايا الاجتماعية والاقتصادية والقانونية والأخلاقية للإنترنت.
Giles died unexpectedly 17 years ago now.
توفي جايلز بشكل مفاجئ منذ 17 سنة.
And I have learned to live without him,
وقد تعلمت مع كيفية التعايش مع فقدانه
and I have learned to live without his need of me.
وكذا التعايش مع عدم اعتماده علي.
Philanthropy is all that I do now.
وأصبح العمل الخيري هو مركز اهتمامي الآن.
I need never worry about getting lost
وأنا لست قلقة أبدا من أن أتوه
because several charities would quickly come and find me.
لأن هناك العديد من الجمعيات الخيرية التي ستركض للبحث عني.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's one thing to have an idea for an enterprise,
العثور على فكرة مشروع هو أمر،
but as many people in this room will know,
لكن وكما يعلم معظم الناس في هذا الحضور
making it happen is a very difficult thing
فإن جعلها تتحقق هو أمر جد صعب
and it demands extraordinary energy, self-belief and determination,
ويتطلب منكم مجهودًا جبارًا وثقة بالنفس وعزيمة
the courage to risk family and home,
وشجاعة للمخاطرة بالأسرة والمنزل
and a 24/7 commitment that borders on the obsessive.
والالتزام 7/24 إلى حد الهوس بما تفعلون.
So it's just as well that I'm a workaholic.
ورغم أني مدمنة عمل،
I believe in the beauty of work when we do it properly and in humility.
إلا أنني أؤمن بجمالية العمل عندما يؤدى بإتقان وتواضع.
Work is not just something I do when I'd rather be doing something else.
العمل ليس مجرد مهمة أقوم بها عندما أكون أفضل القيام بشيء آخر.
We live our lives forward.
فنحن نعيش حياتنا متطلعين للأمام،
So what has all that taught me?
فماذا تعلمت من كل ذلك؟
I learned that tomorrow's never going to be like today,
تعلمت أن الغد لن يكون أبدا كاليوم،
and certainly nothing like yesterday.
وبالتأكيد لن يكون كالبارحة.
And that made me able to cope with change,
وهذا جعلني قادرة على مواجهة التغيير،
indeed, eventually to welcome change,
بل الترحيب في النهاية بالتغيير،
though I'm told I'm still very difficult.
ومع ذلك فقد أخبرت بأني ما زلت صعبة المراس.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)